原视频名：SpaceX's 'Wet' Fleet Gives Up On Catching Falling Fairings
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/8wdo6P84TGA
原视频发布日期：20210411
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
Last week we found out that two high-profile members of SpaceX's fleet are leaving for new opportunities.
上周 我们发现两艘SpaceX船队的有名的船只即将退出 并寻找新的机会
Over the last couple of years Ms. Tree and Ms. Chief have been working on fairing recovery
在过去的几年里 树女士和首席女士一直在负责整流罩的回收工作
using their massive nets to try to catch the fairings discarded by rockets.
用她们的大网试图捕捉被火箭丢弃的整流罩
Now these fairings are flying vehicles in their own right
那么这些整流罩本身就是飞行器了 对吧
with control systems navigation reaction control thrusters and steerable parafoils
带有控制系统 导航系统 反推力系统推进器(RCS)和可操纵的翼伞
that allow them to navigate through re-entry and down to a gentle touchdown on the ocean.
使它们能在再入大气过程中进行导航 并在海面上平稳着陆
Now the fairings cost millions of dollars each
那么这些整流罩每个都要花费数百万美元
and when I was at SpaceX's factory,
而当我在SpaceX的工厂里
you could see that the fairing manufacturer just took a huge section of the factory floor on its own.
你可以看到 整流罩制造商就这样把工厂里的一大块地方给占了
So I can see why recovery was justified.
所以我可以理解为什么回收是合理的
So both ships had made successful catches in their career using the massive nets
那么这两艘船在它们的职业生涯中都曾利用巨大的网成功地捕获过整流罩
but the experience hasn't all been good
但这样的回收并不总是成功的
and many more of the fairings have been recovered after a soft landing in the water.
同时更多的整流罩在水中软着陆后被回收
Perhaps more importantly there have been a few incidents where things went really wrong.
也许更重要的是 有几次回收的时候真的出了问题
Sometimes the fairings hit the net
有时整流罩撞到网子上
but then were pulled off and damaged as the parafoils failed to separate.
但后来由于翼伞未能分离 导致整流罩被其拉力撕开
And after some rough seas we've seen ships come back with damaged nets
而在经历了一些糟糕的海况之后 我们看到船只会带着损坏的网子回来了
or even missing arms just due to the problems of navigating such unwieldy vessels on the high seas.
甚至连网子的支撑臂都搞丢了 因为在公海上驾驶这种笨重的船只会出问题
But I think perhaps most importantly the fairings recovered from the water
但我认为最重要的可能是从水中回收的整流罩
have been reflown successfully without any issues that we know of.
已经成功地重新飞行 而且没有任何我们知道的问题
I mean beyond losing the sound dampening panels that are used to protect sensitive payloads
我是说除了失去用于保护敏感载荷的降噪板之外
so while SpaceX initially had high hopes for flawless fairing recovery
那么 虽然SpaceX最初对整流罩的完美回收寄予厚望
they've now had enough experience and got enough data to show that
但是他们现在已经有了足够的经验和数据来证明
the benefit of a dry fairing recovery isn't worth the extra costs and risks associated with it.
干式整流罩回收的好处并不值得为此付出的额外成本和风险
And also with the majority of SpaceX flights being Starlink launches
而且SpaceX(目前)的大部分飞行都是Starlink的发射
there's no extra effort needed to convince the customer
不需要额外的努力来说服客户
that reflown and fairing is completely free of salt water.
那些飞过的整流罩能完全免受盐水的影响
So Ms. Chief and Ms. Tree are leaving the SpaceX fleet.
那么首席女士和树女士就要离开SpaceX的船队了
They've been stripped of their giant nets and other special equipment
她们已经被拆掉了巨大的网子和其他特殊设备
and as they left the harbor we saw the classic navy salute or marine salute.
而当他们离开港口时 我们看到了经典的海军礼仪或者船舶礼仪
I don't know.
我不知道
Spraying water at the back as they set their course for Louisiana for new jobs.
在后面喷水 与此同时她们为路易斯安那州的新工作设定了路线
It's important to note that they are leaving the SpaceX fleet
需要注意的是 她们要离开SpaceX船队了
but they weren't really owned and operated directly by SpaceX.
但她们并不是真的由SpaceX直接拥有和运营的
I believe these vessels are like SEACOR Marine and Guice Oceanic.
我相信这些船应该是由SEACOR Marine和Guice Offshore(口胡)拥有和运营的
I don't know.
我也不太清楚
So anyway yeah its fairing recovery is still gonna happen
那么不管怎么说 是的  整流罩回收还是会进行的
but instead of landing on a ship by carefully matching the course and hitting the net
但不会是降落到船上 导致这艘船需要仔细地匹配航线并进行网上回收
they're gonna land gently in the water where they will be a ship will rendezvous with them and recover them.
而是轻轻地降落在水中 在那附近他们会有一艘船与之会合并进行回收
And this new ship that was assigned for the latest launch is the Shelia Bordelon operated by Bordelon Marine
而这艘被指定为最近一次发射的整流罩回收的新船是Shelia Bordelon号 由Bordelon Marine运营
and it's described as an ultra light intervention vessel.
而它被描述为一艘超轻型油井干预作业船
It's mainly been working in the offshore oil business.
它主要在海上石油行业工作
And they talk about how it can use remotely operated vehicles
而且他们还谈到了它是如何能使用远程操作载具的
to perform work up to three kilometers underwater and it has a crane able to go that deep.
甚至可以在水下三公里处进行工作 而且它的吊车可以进入那么深的水底
I don't think they're recovering any fairings from underwater
当然我不认为他们会从水下回收任何整流罩
but point is that's what it's been designed for.
但重点是 这就是这艘船的设计目的
So yeah this ship has been practicing fairing recovery off the coast for the last few weeks.
那么是的 这艘船在过去的几周一直在沿海实践整流罩回收
2021.04.07 Starlink V1.0-L23
And Wednesday's Starlink launch number 23 was its first attempt to do it for real
周三的Starlink L23发射的整流罩回收是它第一次真正的尝试
and a day later it returned to port with a fairing half on its deck.
而在一天后 它回到了港口 甲板上有一半的整流罩
So I'm presuming at this point that they do have enough data to know that it's worth their time and effort
那么我推测 在此时 他们确实有足够的数据 知道这是值得他们花费时间和精力
if it wasn't they could just build the fairings without any of the extra recovery gear
如果不是这样 他们就可以只做(一次性)整流罩 而不需要任何额外的回收装置
and that would make them lighter and save money.
而这将使整流罩更轻 并节省资金
I'm not sure we'll see any other space launch providers
我不确定我们会看到任何其他的航天发射提供方
investing in fairing recovery based on SpaceX's experience
根据SpaceX的经验 投资整流罩的回收工作
even although we are seeing some other launch providers
尽管我们看到一些其他发射提供方
really starting to take steps towards booster recovery.
真正开始采取措施去进行助推器的回收
So anyway while we're on the subject of SpaceX's navy it's worth talking about the rest of their fleet.
那么无论如何 当我们在谈论SpaceX的船队这个主题时 也值得谈论他们船队的其他部分
The company actually has a substantial number of marine vessels that they use for its operations.
SpaceX实际上有大量的海洋船只用于其运营
They have ships for the recovery of the Dragon capsules.
他们有用于回收龙飞船的船只
They have the drone ships for recovering the boosters.
他们有无人船来回收助推器
And of course they have tugs and support ships that are used to move the barges and support them.
当然 他们还有拖船和支援船 用于移动驳船并进行支持
And now if you're really interested in all the comings and goings of SpaceX's wet fleet,
而现在如果你对SpaceX船队的来龙去脉感兴趣的话
then I'm going to say Gavin Cornwell he runs the SpaceX fleet.com and he has a patreon.
那么我要说的是Gavin Cornwell 他经营着spacexfleet.com 同时还有patreon
He's been tracking all these operations in far more detail than I could ever manage.
他一直在跟踪所有这些任务 比我说得更具体
So actually let's talk about them.
那么说实在的 我们来谈谈他们吧
First we're going to start with the drone ships.
首先我们要从无人船开始说起
The gigantic landing pads that sit in the middle of the ocean
(SpaceX的无人船就是)位于海洋中央的巨大的着陆场
and provide a safe place for the boosters to touch down after their flight to space.
并为助推器飞往太空后提供一个安全的着陆地点
These are referred to by the acronym ASDS, Autonomous Spaceport Drone Ship.
这些无人船的缩写为ASDS 全称自主太空港无人船
While they might look like dumb barges towed by tugs, they've got their own onboard propulsion
虽然它们可能看起来像由卡车拖船拖着的笨驳船 但它们有自己的船载推进器
that keeps them in place against the forces of oceanic currents and weather.
使它们能够抵御洋流和天气的力量 保持在原地不动
During the landing operations they can hold their positions within about three meters.
在着陆任务中 它们的位置精度可以保持在3米以内
So there's three of them.
那么现在有三艘这样的船只
All of them with names very much inspired by the work of scottish sci-fI author Iain M. Banks.
它们的名字都是受苏格兰科幻作家伊恩·M·班克斯的作品启发
There's Of Course I Still Love You(OCISLY) which has been the primary east coast ocean landing site.
其中一艘叫当然我还爱你 (OCISLY) 它一直是东海岸的主要海上着陆场
There's Just Read The Instructions(JRTI) which started as a west coast landing ship
还有只要读下说明书 (JRTI) 它最初是西海岸的着陆船
but was then moved to the east coast to support the more rapid launch cadence in the last couple of years.
但随后被转移到东海岸 以支持在过去几年中更快速的发射节奏
And finally still under construction there is A Shortfall Of Gravitas(ASOG)
最后还在建设中的是引力不足 (ASOG)
and that will be used to restore ASDS recovery option for from a Vandenberg.
这将被用来恢复范登堡的ASDS回收能力
So they were all constructed in Louisiana
那么它们都是在路易斯安那州建造的
and to get to the west coast incidentally the JRTI had to go through the Panama Canal
之后要去西海岸的话 顺便说一下 JRTI必须通过巴拿马运河
but it's actually too wide in its final configuration.
但实际上它的最终形状太宽了
So the landing pad extensions the wings like along the side.
所以着陆台的扩展就像沿边的机翼一样延伸
Those were built but they weren't loaded onto the deck of JRTI
这些都是(一起)制造出来的 但它们并没有被装到JRTI的甲板上
so we could navigate the canal.
这样才可以在运河上航行
And once on the west coast the pad extensions were lifted off
一旦到了西海岸 平台的延伸部分就被抬起来了
and then welded on there to match the final configuration.
然后焊接在那里 以匹配最终的形状
And that meant for the return trip they had to cut these off again
而这意味着在回程时 他们不得不再次把这些东西剪掉
put them on the deck travel through the canal
放在甲板上 穿越运河
and then reattach them on the east coast.
然后在东海岸重新安装
Also by the way JRTI it's the second SpaceX drone ship with this name.
另外顺便说一下JRTI是SpaceX第二艘用这个名字命名的无人船
There was an earlier one that was used for landing attempts in 2015
早先还有一艘在2015年被用于着陆尝试
when they were still working on the problem.
当时他们还在研究着陆问题
And I guess that some lessons they might have learned during this resulted in changes to OCISLY
而我猜想 他们在这期间可能吸取了一些教训 导致了OCISLY的改变
and that would actually be the first drone ship to be used and to recover a booster.
而这将是第一艘实际回收助推器的无人船
I think they probably just scrap the original JRTI.
我想他们可能就直接放弃了原来的JRTI
And the current one follows the design of OCISLY.
而现在的这个JRTI则是沿用了OCISLY的设计
And I'm going to say that as a fan of Iain M. Banks those names never get old.
而我要说的是 作为伊恩·M·班克斯的粉丝 这些名字永远不会过时
I was delighted to see Richard Garriott going to the bottom of the ocean
我很高兴看到Richard Garriott去了海底
and there were ships called the Limiting Factor.
而(他搭乘的)一些船名为极限因子
It was fabulous.
那真是太神奇了
So anyway while those drone ships have their own propulsion with the azimuth thrusters to hold position
那么不管怎么说 虽然那些无人船使用自己的全向推进器来保持位置
they don't actually travel long distances under their own power.
但它们实际上并不依靠自己的动力进行长途旅行
Instead they're towed to the landing sites by tugs
而是由拖船把它们拖到着陆点的
and there's quite a few different tugs that they've used over the years
而这些年来 他们使用了不少不同的拖船
and I think there's nothing special about these.
而我觉得这些没有什么特别的地方
There's currently the Hawk, the Finn Falgout, Lauren Foss, the Hollywood.
目前有霍克号 芬恩法尔戈特号 劳伦福斯号 好莱坞号
They don't have anything special about them but they can be used to move these things around.
它们没有什么特别的地方 但是可以用来移动这些东西
So the drone ships also have a support ship assigned to them for operations
那么无人船也会配有一艘支援船 用于作业
and these are the vessels actually have the crew on them.
而这些船只上实际上都有船员
And they'll have communications equipment and other special gear that's needed to help with the recovery.
而他们会有通讯设备和其他特殊装备 以助于回收
Now this has usually been the GO Quest on the east coast
那么 东海岸通常是GO寻求号
and on the few droner ship recoveries on the west coast has been the NRC Quest.
而在西海岸的无人船回收则是NRC寻求号
And these are operated by different operators right.
而这些都是由不同的运营方运营的 对吧
GO I think is Guice Offshore with a G and NRC is National Response Corporation.
GO是Guice Offshore的缩写 NRC则是National Response Corporation的缩写
More importantly though NRC quest which was operated on the west coast
更重要的是 NRC寻求号是在西海岸运营的
it was the primary recovery vessel for all the Dragon one capsules
它是龙1飞船的主要回收船
which yeah they landed in the pacific and it would be picked up put on the deck
是的 龙1飞船降落在太平洋上 会被抓起放在甲板上
and the ship would return to port as quickly as possible
而船只会尽快返回港口
so they could offload the science experiments from the ISS and hand it off to handlers on the ground
这样他们就可以把国际空间站上返回的科学实验卸下来 交给地面上的工作人员了
Now for Dragon 2 both crew and cargo vessels are intended to land on the east coast
那么龙2飞船的载人和货运版都打算在东海岸着陆了
and now that these might contain crew. There's actually a pair of recovery ships so there's redundancy.
而现在这些飞船可能包含乘员 实际上有两艘回收船来负责这些事 所以有冗余
There's GO Searcher and GO Navigator
那么负责这些事的船是GO搜寻者和GO领航者
and these are configured identically with the recovery crane and other support equipment.
而这些船只都配置有相同的回收起重机和其他支持设备
But they also have a helipad
但他们也有一个直升机停机坪
and that's important if there's an emergency and they need to get crew back to shore quickly.
而如果有紧急情况 他们就需要迅速地将船员送回岸上 那么停机坪这一点就很重要
So these two ships are also being used for fairing recovery in the past
那么这两艘船在过去也被用来进行整流罩的回收工作
but I imagine that that might be a short-term thing.
但我想这可能是一件比较短期的事情
really not clear but that is a capability they have.
具体真的不清楚 但整流罩回收也是它们的一种能力
In the last few months of course we've seen two of the biggest additions to the fleet
在过去的几个月里 当然我们已经看到了船队中最大的两个添加
with an eye on future offshore rocket operations of Starship.
这将着眼于Starship未来的海上火箭运营
Phobos and Deimos a pair of former oil drilling platforms
福波斯和得摩斯 它们是一对前石油钻井平台
apparently acquired at a bargain basement price
显然是低价获得的
as the demand for oil cratered in the last year.
由于去年对石油的需求急剧下降
And these massive platforms were costing millions of dollars to upkeep
而这些大型平台的维护费用高达数百万美元
so their owners were happy to get rid of them.
所以它们的主人很乐意把它们处理掉
I hear a platform of this size with all the equipment costs on the order of half a billion dollars
我听说这么大的一个平台 所有的设备费用算起来在5亿美元左右
and SpaceX managed to pick them up for less than one percent of this.
而SpaceX设法以不到其百分之一的价格拿下它们
Although I imagine that that might not include all of the equipment
虽然我猜想这可能不包括所有的设备
which might be returned to the previous owner.
这些设备可能会被返还给前主人
So anyway these are currently being stripped down to their structure
那么 无论如何 这些钻井平台目前正在被拆解至主体结构部分
but given that the plan is to literally catch the boosters in the launch support hardware
但鉴于计划中是要在发射支持设备中真正地抓住助推器
and eliminate the need for landing legs
并不再需要着陆腿
we can only really imagine what they might look like when they're finally done.
我们只能想象它们最终完成时的样子
Then again plans change
不过计划还是会变的
so we'll have to basically see how things take shape over the coming year
那么 我们基本上要看未来一年的情况了
to get an idea how these end up looking.
这样才能了解它们最终的样子
Finally I think I need to give a shout out to the permanent crew members of the SpaceX navy
最后 我想我有必要给SpaceX船队的常驻船员们点个赞
an elusive group of characters who we rarely see.
一群我们很少见到的神秘人物
They practically live on the drone ships.
他们几乎是生活在无人船上
These crew members go into danger to make sure that the still smoking boosters are secured quickly
这些船员们为了确保还在冒烟的助推器能被迅速地保护起来 不惜铤而走险
before the rest of the crew who have much more sense of self-preservation are allowed near.
在其他有更多自我保护意识的人被允许靠近之前进行这些工作
I'm of course talking about the Octograbbers
当然 我说的是操作八爪鱼(小八)的人
which emerge from their garages moments after boost landing.
他们在助推着陆后的瞬间从车库中出现
They roll under the rocket and then secure it in place
把小八推到火箭下面 然后把它固定在原地
that there's no chance of the booster falling over in high seas.
这样助推器就不可能在公海上(倾倒并)摔下来
We've actually seen a few boosters lost after successful landings
事实上 我们已经看到一些助推器在成功着陆后被搞坏了
because Octograbber either didn't exist at the time or wasn't able to help.
要么是因为小八当时还不存在 要么就是帮不上忙
2019.04.11 Arabsat-6A
I guess my favorite one most interesting one is the one of the Falcon Heavy cores
我想我最喜欢的 也觉得最有趣的一个案例 是那次重型猎鹰芯级的回收
which landed safely but there were subtle differences to the booster design
那次芯级安全着陆 但因为助推器的设计有细微的差别
and that meant the Octograbber wasn't able to deploy to secure it
而这就意味着无法部署小八来把它的固定
and the booster fell over on the way home.
而助推器就在回家的路上摔倒了
I mean the saying
我是指 那句谚语
For every great booster there's a great Octograbber securing them or something like that.
对于每一个伟大的助推器 都有一个伟大的小八来固定它 或者类似的话
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]